<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Staging Effective Altruism</title>
	<atom:link href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:14:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Is Life So Hard? 4 Things You Can Do About It</title>
		<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/why-is-life-so-hard-4-things-you-can-do-about-it/</link>
					<comments>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/why-is-life-so-hard-4-things-you-can-do-about-it/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:14:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/?p=21</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you are wondering why life is so hard, then there is probably something missing from your life. Ask yourself, are you living a life of complacency or a life of purpose? Regardless of how you define “purpose,” you know whether you are chasing it or settling for less. Interestingly enough, you will face challenges ... <a title="Why Is Life So Hard? 4 Things You Can Do About It" class="read-more" href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/why-is-life-so-hard-4-things-you-can-do-about-it/" aria-label="More on Why Is Life So Hard? 4 Things You Can Do About It">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you are wondering why life is so hard, then there is probably something missing from your life. Ask yourself, are you living a life of complacency or a life of purpose?</p>
<p>Regardless of how you define “purpose,” you know whether you are chasing it or settling for less. Interestingly enough, you will face challenges in both cases. The only difference is how you feel at the end of the day.</p>
<p>Why Is Life So Hard?<br />
When you question why life is so hard and you are chasing your purpose, you know there is something that makes everything worthwhile. As “risk-free” as settling may appear, you will bear the burden of never reaching your true potential. You will always be wondering if there is more to life than the one you have lived.</p>
<p>While the journey to change your life is not always easy, it should ultimately be enjoyable. You should enjoy learning more about yourself, your goals, and your motivations.</p>
<p>If you find yourself wondering if life gets any better, here’re some tips for you:</p>
<p>1. Surviving Versus Thriving<br />
Every day, you have two choices. You can choose to listen to the loud voice of fear and self-doubt, or you can listen to the quiet voice of confidence and purpose.</p>
<p>The quiet voice of confidence is the voice that is pushing you to chase your dream life. Your dream life is the life you would live if you did not have any responsibilities or obstacles. If you are wondering why life is so hard, you could be struggling to accomplish your purpose. You may want to start a business, but you need consistent income from your current job. There could be the challenge of overcoming a disadvantage you were born with or the environment you grew up in. Whatever the reason, there is a struggle that you have not conquered yet.</p>
<p>While you may feel you are making the best decision with the cards you have been dealt with, that doesn’t change the fact that you are meant to do more than survive. As essential as survival is, you don’t want to reach the end of your life never having truly lived. There are plenty of people who find their last days filled with regret because they always succumbed to their fears.</p>
<p>If you want to make your life easier, then stop putting your dreams on hold. Start taking small steps toward accomplishing them each day. Also, make sure you celebrate your small wins. This will help you build momentum and enjoy the process, so you don’t feel like quitting when challenges arise.</p>
<p>Even though you may not enjoy failure, it is okay to fail at trying something new. In fact, failure is a great sign to know that you are chasing your purpose and listening to your voice of confidence. Continue to learn from your mistakes and allow them to transform you into your ideal self.</p>
<p>2. Emotions Run High<br />
If knowledge is power, then knowing what to do with said knowledge should make life easier. However, you will find that is not always the case. In fact, you can go out on a very stable limb and conclude that most people know what they should be doing.</p>
<p>Each year, close to half of the population makes a New Year’s Resolution. They have a plan of attack and they know what needs to happen for them to accomplish their desired results. Yet, less than 10% of people actually achieve their resolution each year. [1]</p>
<p>This begs the question: Why is life so hard when you have a plan you know will work?</p>
<p>There are plenty of salespeople who know if they reach out to a certain number of people each day, they will have a successful business. Some couples know if they listen and consider each other’s feelings before taking action, their relationship will benefit. Whether you are talking about professional or personal goals, you know the action needed for success.</p>
<p>The disconnect occurs when you haven’t taken your emotions into consideration. It is difficult to consider someone’s feelings when you feel taken for granted or unappreciated. It can be difficult to make the next phone call when the last five people said no to you. There is an emotional aspect of life that makes doing the right thing difficult.</p>
<p>Studies show you can increase the likelihood of you overcoming your emotions when you use the ‘If-Then Principle’ to prepare yourself ahead of time. [2] The way it works is you create your response beforehand, so your emotions don’t get the best of you later.</p>
<p>For example, if you have friends who eat unhealthily, you can say, “If I go to lunch with them, then I will order a salad.” When you are dealing with sales, you may say, “If I am told no, then I will keep making calls until I hear yes”. As simple as it sounds, knowing how you will handle setbacks is what sets apart those who are surviving from those who are thriving.</p>
<p>3. Burning the Candle on Both Ends<br />
If you are still questioning why life is so hard, then you need to ask yourself if you are working too hard. You probably chuckled a little at the statement, but humor me.</p>
<p>Your life is a cumulation of your experiences. Some of those experiences are going to be more pleasant than others. If you find yourself with an unbalanced amount of unpleasant experiences, you need to determine if you are setting unrealistic goals for yourself.</p>
<p>For example, if someone sets a goal to lose 60lbs in 30 days, they may not know how unlikely that goal is to accomplish. If they knew the average weight loss regiment would recommend losing one to two pounds a week, then they would know two pounds a day is unhealthy. Nevertheless, if you set an unrealistic goal, you are going to feel deflated when you miss it.</p>
<p>Life gets even more difficult as you try to find a way to accomplish the achievable in an unrealistic timeline. You miss the fact that you have achieved tremendous progress along the way because you feel the failure of not achieving your goal. This can continue to be frustrating and have you asking yourself why is life so hard.</p>
<p>The best way to overcome this feeling of frustration is to give yourself more time. [3] You will be surprised how much lower your stress levels are when you give yourself more time.</p>
<p>Do you recall a time you had an assignment due in school or a project due at work and you needed more time? You know your presentation would be flawless if you only had another day or two. Then, by a stroke of luck, the meeting or deadline was moved back a week because someone got sick or had a conflict in attending. How amazing do you feel when you find yourself with more time than you expected? Go ahead and give yourself the additional time and see how it changes your perception of the situation.</p>
<p>4. Looking in All the Wrong Places<br />
Life can be really hard if you are only thinking about everything wrong in your life. Believe me, I know there is a lot wrong in the world, but there is plenty right in the world, too.</p>
<p>You get to choose what you want to focus on. If you train your mind to only recognize what is wrong with the world, it makes it almost impossible to see the opportunities. Imagine someone who only watches the news. Most people acknowledge the news is full of negative stories that create fear, anger, and frustration. As a result, your perception of the world will be skewed by the constant bombardment of negative information.</p>
<p>A negative perception can also be created by associating with people who are always complaining about something. Whether they are complaining about their family, their relationships, or their job, it will cause you to ponder about the issues in your life.</p>
<p>For you to overcome a negative mindset, you need to take two actions. First, you need to reduce the negative information you are absorbing. You will need to spend less time watching the news and you need to reduce the amount of time you spend with negative people. This can be difficult if the negative person is a family member or a close friend. However, if their mindset has you question why is life so hard, you owe it to yourself to change your associations.</p>
<p>The second thing you need to do is create a positivity journal. You don’t need to write in it every day, but you should read it every day. You should start each day reading about all the things you love about your life. This will help you appreciate the joys of your life even more because those joys are not being drowned out by the day to day challenges.</p>
<p>Final Thoughts<br />
The reason why life is so hard can vary from person to person. Your personal growth and transformation should comfort you every time you look back and recognize how far you have come.</p>
<p>Don’t grow discouraged when things don’t happen as quickly as you want. Instead, focus on the fact that you are taking a step in the right direction each day. If you are better each day than you were the previous day, you will love you the person you become when it is all said and done.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/why-is-life-so-hard-4-things-you-can-do-about-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is effective altruism? How could it be improved?</title>
		<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/what-is-effective-altruism-how-could-it-be-improved/</link>
					<comments>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/what-is-effective-altruism-how-could-it-be-improved/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:13:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/?p=18</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The EA community has been convulsing since FTX. There&#8217;s been lots of discontent, but almost no public discussion between community leaders, and little in the way of a constructive suggestions for what could change. In this post, I offer a reconceptualisation of what the EA community is and then use that to sketch some ideas ... <a title="What is effective altruism? How could it be improved?" class="read-more" href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/what-is-effective-altruism-how-could-it-be-improved/" aria-label="More on What is effective altruism? How could it be improved?">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The EA community has been convulsing since FTX. There&#8217;s been lots of discontent, but almost no public discussion between community leaders, and little in the way of a constructive suggestions for what could change. In this post, I offer a reconceptualisation of what the EA community is and then use that to sketch some ideas for how to do good better together.</p>
<p>I’m writing this purely in my personal capacity as a long-term member of the effective altruism community. I drafted this at the start of 2023, in large part to help me process my own thoughts. The ideas here are still, by my lights, dissatisfyingly underdeveloped. But I’m posting it now, in its current state and with minimal changes, because it&#8217;s suddenly relevant to topical discussions about how to run the Effective Ventures Foundation and the Centre for Effective Altruism and I don&#8217;t know if I would ever make time to polish it.</p>
<p>[I&#8217;m grateful to Ben West, Chana Messinger, Luke Freeman, Jack Lewars, Nathan Young, Peter Brietbart, Sam Bernecker, and Will Troy for their comments on this. All errors are theirs mine]</p>
<p>Summary<br />
We can think of effective altruists as participants in a market for maximum impact activities. It’s much like a local farmers’ market, except people are buying and selling goods and services for how best to help others.<br />
Just like people in a market, EAs don’t all share the same goal &#8211; a marketplace isn’t an army. Rather, people have different goals, based on their different accounts of what matters. The participants can agree, however, that they all want there to be a marketplace to allow them to meet and trade; this market is useful because people want different things.<br />
Presumably, the EA market should function as a free, competitive market. This means lots of choice and debate among the participants. It requires the market administrators to operate a level playing-field.<br />
Currently, the EA community doesn’t quite operate like this. The market administrators &#8211; CEA, its staff and trustees &#8211; are also major market participants, i.e. promoting particular ideas and running key organisations. And the market is dominated by one big buyer (i.e. it’s a ‘monopsony’).<br />
I suggest some possible reforms: CEA to have its trustees elected by the community; it should strive to be impartial rather than take a stand on the priorities. I don’t claim this will solve all the issues, but it should help. I&#8217;m sure there are other implications of the market model I&#8217;ve not thought of.<br />
These reforms seem sensible even without any of EA’s recent scandals. I do, however, explain how they would likely have helped lessened these scandals too.<br />
I’ve tried to resist getting into the minutiae of “how would EA be run if modelled on a free market?” and I would encourage readers also to resist this. I want people to focus on the basic idea and the most obvious implications, not get stuck on the details.<br />
I’m not very confident in the below. It’s an odd mix of ideas from philosophy, politics, and economics. I wrote it up in the hope others can develop the ideas and I can stop ruminating on the “what should FTX mean for EA?” question.<br />
What is EA? A market for maximum-impact altruistic activities<br />
What is effective altruism? It&#8217;s described by the website effectivealtruism.org as a &#8220;research field and practical community that aims to find the best ways to help others, and put them into practice&#8221;. That&#8217;s all well and good, but it&#8217;s not very informative if we want to understand the behaviour of individuals in the community and the functioning of the community as a whole.</p>
<p>An alternative approach is to think of effective altruists, the people themselves, in economic terms. In this case, we might characterise the effective altruism community as a group of individuals participating in a marketplace for maximum impact philanthropic goods and services &#8211; an agora for altruists.</p>
<p>This may initially seem strange, but effective altruism community is somewhat analogous to a local farmers&#8217; market. However, instead of the market stalls offering fruit, vegetables, and so on, the sellers are touting various charities, as well as research into those charities. There are buyers &#8211; donors &#8211; who are looking to get the best value for their money. There’s a social community that’s formed around the market. There are some people whose job it is to run the market, too.</p>
<p>The motivation of the participants in each market may be different: people come to the &#8216;EA market&#8217; for the good of others but go to the farmers&#8217; market for their own good. However, in many other respects, the markets function identically: buyers come to shop around and find the best deal for their money, and sellers are trying to sell as much of their goods as possible.</p>
<p>One key practical difference is that, whilst you can inspect the quality of goods in the farmers’ market yourself (you can see if the fruit is rotten) buyers in the EA market can’t easily test or observe the goods they buy (you don’t see what happens when you, say, donate to AMF). Hence, arguably the key players in the EA market are the research organisations, which provide advice to participants, equivalent to consumer champions, such as Which? in the UK.</p>
<p>What, if anything, about EA is new? Of course, markets are old, as are charities and events around charities. Perhaps what’s new is that this is the first historical example of a marketplace for people explicitly committed to achieving the maximum impact for their altruistic resources, rather than just some impact: some combination of free market economics applied to philanthropy.[1] I suspect that simply creating a market for maximum impact altruism is an extremely important &#8211; and so far unrecognised &#8211; achievement of the community.</p>
<p>Considering EA as like a farmers’ market, you don’t have to look hard to identify equivalent structures. In EA, the marketplace itself is run by various arms of the Effective Ventures Foundation (EVF, which formerly used to be called, somewhat confusingly, CEA). CEA runs the EAG and EAGx conferences (the market days), the EA forum (the market noticeboard), the EA handbook (the market catalogue) and the community builder grants (market outreach). 80,000 Hours is the main advertiser for the marketplace. EAFunds is a platform for buyers. Giving What We Can is a buyer’s community. Longview is a club for large buyers that encourage particular purchases. And so on.</p>
<p>Whether or not you like the marketplace analogy, it’s pretty clear EA operates on a ‘hub-and-spoke’ model. There are some common bits that are widely participated in &#8211; the conference, the forum, CEA’s marketing, the social network &#8211; but otherwise there’s quite a lot of separation, with participants congregating by cause areas.</p>
<p>If we see the EA community as a market, what follows about how it would work?<br />
It seems apt to understand effective altruists as engaging in a certain kind of economic activity. Given that, but that we aren&#8217;t used to think of EA this way, what can we say about how the EA market will function? We&#8217;ll come back to questions of how it should, morally-speaking, function in a moment.</p>
<p>One main takeaway is that we should conceive of effective altruists as functioning like any other economic agents, just with a rather unusual set of preferences. We should expect them to pursue their own self-interest. We should not expect them to be moral saints, or to be immune to ordinary human flaws and vices; this might sound obvious, but I’ve often got the impression that EAs think of themselves, and particularly their leaders, as fully selfless, perfectly rational, and so on: no, we’re all just people, squishy bags of flesh attached to bones, evolved from apes and living on the surface of a rock flying through space.</p>
<p>Something that follows from this first observation is that EA is not a collective project. We are not like an army, working together for the same goal, or, as Holden Karnofsky has suggested, the crew of a ship. People may want to ‘do the most good’, but have different conceptions of &#8216;the good&#8217;. People with the same moral views might be analogous to the crew of a ship, but not the market as a whole. If you really want to keep the ship analogy, we&#8217;re like multiple ships, with many people undecided on which ship to join or split between multiple ships.</p>
<p>In the market paradigm, the buyers and sellers don’t have, or need to have, much in common. The butcher, baker, and candlestick-maker each want to maximise profits for themselves, rather than the collective. As Adam Smith put it, relating to conventional markets, “It is not from the benevolence (kindness) of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest”.</p>
<p>It can be rational for participants to press for their own interests at the cost of others. Participants can and will believe that their products are superior; they may well think others are snake oil salesmen. Although the buyers all seek &#8216;the best value for their money&#8217;, as they see it, they do not think of &#8216;best value&#8217; the same way. Indeed, that’s the point. There is a market because people have a diversity of preferences and they want a single place to go and shop &#8211; if you only want one item, there may be little point going to the market. Buyers and sellers with shared interests may group together to increase their negotiating power.</p>
<p>Perhaps the only thing the participants will, collectively, have in common is that they want there to be a market and, what’s more, for it to be run freely and fairly. As a whole, they’ll want to avoid corruption, nepotism, arbitrariness, dishonesty, etc. If you’re an apple seller, you don’t want your stall to be hidden at the back, whilst the other apple seller gets pride of place because he’s friends with the guy that runs the market.</p>
<p>The shared aim of wanting a ‘free and fair market’ is fairly minimal, and desired only because it is in their individual interests. There isn’t some further, substantial goal all the participants need to share; it would be surprising if there was one.</p>
<p>As a consequence of their different interests, it will be rational for individual participants in either market to bend or break the rules in their favour, establish favourable or monopoly positions for themselves, and so on, if they can. This problem doesn’t go away in the EA marketplace. If anything, it’s sharpened: rather than trying to get the best deal for yourself (as you see it), you aim to get the best for others (as you see it), so there some moral reason to bend the rules in your (moral view’s) favour. Equally, participants may be annoyed if they see others abusing their power to promote their own interests.</p>
<p>How, in broad terms, should the EA market be organised? As a free market<br />
I’ll discuss some specific changes for EA in the next section.</p>
<p>If we ask “how should a farmers’ market operate?”, an obvious, but not very informative answer, is “to bring about the best outcomes”. Fine, but how do we know what those are? Perhaps some social planner should decide what would be best for people, then force the market to produce those goods. That, indeed, is the approach preferred by socialists and, to a greater extent, communists.</p>
<p>The standard answer, the one out of vanilla economic theory -and the one I imagine most EAs would agree to generally &#8211; is that there should be a free market. Individual consumers choose what they want, producers react to demand, and what is ultimately produced is decided by ‘the market’. The free market is the means to the end of producing the best outcomes.</p>
<p>Given that the EA community seems to be a market, like any other, the presumption is that it should be structured like any other free market unless there are sufficiently good reasons to deviate from this.</p>
<p>I don’t want to get into the minutiae of exactly how markets should be run. It’s not my speciality and I suppose that focusing on details will be distracting from the broad strokes.</p>
<p>I suspect some will object to this model: the purpose of EA is, in the end, to &#8216;do the most good&#8217;, not ‘operate as a free market’, so if we already know what the particular priorities are, shouldn’t we just push people towards those? Here, we need to be careful to distinguish both means from ends and, also, the perspective of individuals from the collective.</p>
<p>This situation of individuals thinking ‘I know what’s best’ is, of course, essential to the functioning of an ordinary free market: you want sellers to create and tout goods to customers, provide choice, compete over price, etc. because this allows consumers to get better deals.</p>
<p>However, we still want sellers to compete in the free market, and to resist attempts by sellers to distort the market in their favour. There’s a reason governments have bodies that work to maintain competition and break up monopolies.</p>
<p>Given this, there’s an important distinction between the mindset of individual participants and the organisers of the market. The participants are entitled, indeed encouraged, to advocate for what they think is best (within the rules, whatever they are). But the organisers of the market should maintain a level playing-field, remain studiously impartial between these and only intervene to correct market inefficiencies (I leave open how much correction is warranted). It&#8217;s through competition that the buyers get the best deals. Ultimately, the question of “who’s right?” should be determined by the participants in the market, not its organisers. You get the best outcomes because, not in spite, of their being a level playing field. You want a free market as the means of achieving good outcomes &#8211; it&#8217;s not an end in itself.</p>
<p>Although it’s tempting for participants in the EA market to nudge the moral market in their favour, i.e. ensure more of their preferred goods are sold, doing so seems objectionably paternalistic. It combines arrogance &#8211; “I know better than others” &#8211; but also suggests insecurity &#8211; “I do not believe my ideas would win in a free market, so I must intervene”. If we think state interference, monopolies and so on, are bad in ordinary markets, we should object to them in high-impact philanthropic markets too.</p>
<p>Lurking in the background is a concept of fairness. We’re talking about morality, so don’t we need to decide on the correct theory of morality first to run the moral market? The obvious, if not perfectly simple, principle to appeal to here is Rawls’ Veil of Ignorance: how would you like the market to be run if you didn’t know who you would be in it? You could be a buyer or seller, and you could have few or many resources.</p>
<p>Given this, we can distinguish between whether some change to the structure of the market is good or bad for an individual from whether it promotes or reduces fairness. I suspect we should praise those who strive to make the effective altruism market fair, especially when this is counter to their narrow interests.</p>
<p>The market itself will need to be organised by someone, and could well have various functions, such as advertising the market as a whole to potential customers, and deciding who gets which stalls. But it should not favour particular goods or services.</p>
<p>To what extent is EA functioning differently from this right now?<br />
The effective altruism community is full of wonderful, smart, intelligent, thoughtful caring people &#8211; many of the best people I know. I find it a continued source of inspiration. My aim here, however, is to flag some ways in which effective altruism, as a system, could possibly work better. Although my intention is to highlight how things might be improved, I don’t want this to detract from the much excellent work that people do. My focus is on the overall functioning of the ‘market’. I don’t think I have much, if anything, to say about the behaviour of the small buyers and sellers. This is consistent with, indeed follows from, conceiving of it as a market and wanting it to run as a free-market. If you have a well-regulated market and lots of buyers and sellers, the result is a competitive market. Hence, you want to focus on removing the barrier to their being such a market.</p>
<p>I see a few related problem areas.</p>
<p>(1) there is a big overlap between the administrators and the participants in the market.</p>
<p>CEA/EVF is the hub that coordinates the wider movement, but it, and its trustees, are also participants who advocate for particular things. Of the seven total trustees of the US and UK EVF boards, six are current or former &#8216;buyers&#8217; or &#8216;sellers&#8217; in the market. As far as I can tell, Tasha McCauley is the only one not directly involved in another effective altruism organisation. Claire Zabel, Nick Beckstead, Eli Rose, Nicole Ross and Zachary Robinson are all current or former Open Philanthropy employees. Nick Beckstead was the chair of the FTX Foundation. The final trustee is Will MacAskill, who wears more hats in effective altruism than it is easy to list. Aside from being participants in the markets, two of them (Nick and Will) are also major public proponents of a particular market &#8216;outcome&#8217;, namely longtermism (see Nick&#8217;s thesis and Will&#8217;s recent book). This is a bit like having the farmers&#8217; market mostly run by the orange sellers&#8217; association &#8211; arguably non-ideal. CEA promotes a particularly longtermism agenda, as does 80k.</p>
<p>I would like to see CEA/EV acting as something like an impartial regulator, civil service, or public service broadcaster, for EA: it should try to impartially manage things, not take a stand. If you want to be outspoken, then that’s fine, but you should probably let someone else take the reins of organising the market. As the Bible puts it, no man can serve two masters.</p>
<p>To be clear, I don&#8217;t want to blame anyone for the status quo. A charitable and fairly plausible explanation is that the people most passionate about the market would also have views about what the priorities should be &#8211; the products it should produce. So the original participants became organisers. But as EA looks to the future, it seems preferable to move to a split. I imagine some organisers might welcome this change &#8211; it&#8217;s awkward to act as something like a politician and a civil servant.</p>
<p>(2) the central market structure lacks accountability to or oversight by its participants.</p>
<p>The farmers&#8217; market would be accountable to the local government and ultimately, the electorate. Conspicuously, the Effective Venture Foundation, which contains a number of charities, including the Centre for Effective Altruism (CEA), is accountable only to its trustees &#8211; and perhaps, practically, its donors &#8211; and has no democratic elements. This seems non-ideal. CEA, as its name indicates, to some large extent represents the EA movement as a whole, yet there is no formal representation of the EA movement in its decision-making. As the American revolutionaries might have said in this context, “no representation without representation” (rather than “no taxation without representation”).</p>
<p>(3) there’s only one major buyer.</p>
<p>EA is effectively a monopsony. This is the opposite of a monopoly, that is, where there is only one seller. Open Philanthropy comprises something like 60% of the total purchasing power (from eyeballing Ben Todd&#8217;s now out-of-date figures). I don&#8217;t find monopsonies as intuitive as monopolies, but my understanding is that, just like monopolies are bad if you&#8217;re a buyer, monopsonies are bad if you&#8217;re a seller. Because there is only one buyer, you get reduced competition and innovation: organisations aren&#8217;t incentivised to produce goods for other buyers, but instead to focus on what the large buyer wants.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s been discussion in EA about regranting from the major funders &#8211; Open Philanthropy and (formerly) FTX. I take this as recognition that there&#8217;s an issue with funder concentration.</p>
<p>The combination of (1) &#8211; (3) means there’s no/little effective external scrutiny of how EA is run. Who has the incentive, or power, to say “hey guys, is this a great idea?’ who is not already an insider?</p>
<p>There may be lots of other issues too that someone more economically literate would spot.</p>
<p>What should be done?<br />
The most obvious solution for (1) and (2) is to remove the overlap between participants and administrators. One way to do this is for CEA/EV to move to having a partially or fully elected set of trustees. These trustees should ideally not be both ‘poachers’ and ‘gamekeepers’. The central functions in effective altruism strive to be genuinely impartial.</p>
<p>What would the electorate be? Contra Dustin Moskovitz, aka ‘The Sponsor’ who suggests defining the EA community is a ‘non-starter’, there are quite a few options: Giving What We Can members; people who have previously attended EAGs; CEA could become a fee-paying society like many others. I’m sure there are other options. Personally, I like the idea of GWWC members selecting the trustees of CEA: giving 10% is a costly signal and it gives people an incentive to take the pledge. I recognise it&#8217;s too late to do this for the new round of EV/CEA trustees that are being recruited, so this is something to consider for the future.</p>
<p>CEA could be more accountable and allow for more ‘voice’ from the community, even without reforming its structures. One simple thing would be for the CEO(s) to have &#8216;townhall&#8217; meeting at EAGs where people could (anonymously) ask them difficult questions.</p>
<p>I don’t have an easy solution to (3). I think it’s good there is one major buyer, rather than none, and I can’t simply magic up another billionaire. That said, if CEA had democratic elements, it would then have to balance the desires of its major funder with that of the electorate, rather than being so concerned with the former, which seems like progress.</p>
<p>One suggestion for funder concentration that gets mooted is regranting, e.g. Open Phil gives money to a bunch of other people to spend on its behalf. This doesn&#8217;t seem like a very promising solution and we can see why in light of the market analogy: it’s basically like the rich local landowner giving a lot of money to his mates and telling them to buy things in the farmers’ market. If they buy the same things, nothing changes. If they buy different things, he’ll think it was a bad idea. Either way, it’s only a temporary spike in demand. Perhaps the better solution, if the major donor(s) want the market to exist, is to financially support the existence of an impartial market it does not itself run (I recognise someone might argue this already happens, to some degree).</p>
<p>Possibly, if EA was run more conspicuously as an impartial market, it would attract and retain more large ‘buyers’.</p>
<p>Similarly, the econ-literate folk may spot obvious improvements that have not been obvious to me.</p>
<p>How would all this have helped EA with its recent scandals?<br />
I hope that all of the above seemed sensible without appealing directly to SBF, sexual misdemeanours, or racism. But I do think we can see how it would help, to some extent, with those.</p>
<p>SBF. A question we might ask is: why was Sam Bankman-Fried a problem for the EA community? What does it have to do with the wider community that some guy who identified as EA, and was a donor, seems to have committed an enormous crime? I think we can pick this apart by imagining alternatives.</p>
<p>Suppose a big buyer disappears from the marketplace. This would be unfortunate, but there’s no scandal.</p>
<p>Suppose there&#8217;s criminality on the part of some people in the marketplace. This raises general issues of community trust, as well as specifically of policing, but it wouldn’t obviously rock things to the core. And we should expect it to happen. People are still people, even if they participate in the maximum altruism market.</p>
<p>Suppose a major buyer collapses, they are engaged in criminal activity, but their staff are also deeply involved in running the market. This is much more serious because it goes right to the heart of the market. It raises questions about whether the core staff were sufficiently attentive to the health and good running of the market as a whole. One perspective on why SBF-gate shocked EA to its very core was that the people working with SBF at his fund were the same key EAs who run the movement/market, and are key participants in it, eg Will MacAskill and Nick Beckstead.</p>
<p>What if EA were organised along the lines suggested above, with a democratically infused CEA that was not a participant in the market?</p>
<p>For one, it would have contained the problem. Imagine FTX had collapsed, but its staff were just ‘ordinary’ EAs and not involved in running anything else. This would have been a much smaller problem, it not clearly so damning for EA as a whole.</p>
<p>For another, democratic elements would have improved scrutiny. With EA run as a very tight group, there was no one who had the incentives, or the power, to ask probing questions like “hey, is this guy legit? Should we really take his money?” I would absolutely have expected someone to ask those questions about SBF at anonymous townhalls, at which point the CEO of CEA would have to at least think about it.</p>
<p>What about Nick Bostrom and his ‘old email’ case? This struck me as a relatively contained scandal exactly because Nick ‘just’ runs a ‘spoke’ in EA, the Future of Humanity Institute, but he doesn’t (also) have a role in the hub. If I&#8217;m an apple-seller, I don&#8217;t think it has much to do with me if the chief cheese dealer has unpleasant views.</p>
<p>Finally, let’s turn to the scandals about sexual behaviour and consider the case of Owen Cotton-Barratt, the trustee of CEA who recently resigned. A couple of things stick out.</p>
<p>One is that it&#8217;s difficult to police the behaviour of your boss, which is what the community health team had to do. Saliently, the community health knew about the incidents, but didn&#8217;t raise them to the whole board [Chana Messinger commented on a draft on this that the health team &#8220;did bring this to a UK board member&#8221; but not the whole board]. What would have happened if the trustees were elected &#8211; or at least there was greater scrutiny of CEA? Probably, the community health team would have been more accountable to the wider community and would have felt obliged to tell some or all of board who would, in turn, have felt obliged to tell the rest of the board and then act. At that point, the trustee would have made a public statement and/or resigned. They could still have stood for re-election, meaning the community could decide if the matters were sufficiently serious to merit not being re-elected. At least, it seems far less likely this story would have emerged, years later, in the international press, with an open question over whether the community health team had prioritised its boss over the community.</p>
<p>The other is that Owen was, in addition to being a trustee of CEA, also a leading market participant in his role at the Future of Humanity Institute. As well as being non-ideal in itself, this arguably gave him additional influence that made it harder for the community health team to act.</p>
<p>Regarding the wider reports of EA community members being involved in sexual harassment, the complaint about the status quo is that there is a close-knit group of men who control the jobs and so speaking out is dangerous. But, again, if CEA were accountable to the community and separate from other organisations, it makes it much easier for people to raise issues with CEA, and for CEA to be in a stronger position to, say, warn or ban offenders of events.</p>
<p>Closing thoughts<br />
The effective altruism community began with a bunch of smart, idealistic, inexperienced young people about 10 years ago. It has become radically, unexpectedly, successful and then exploded into the public consciousness. Its original institutions were designed pretty much as you might expect a friendly, close-knit group to do, and they worked well when EA was small. But it&#8217;s run into what we might politely call &#8216;growing pains&#8217;. Now EA is big, we need &#8211; reluctantly &#8211; to grow up and develop new institutions that are fit for purpose.</p>
<p>I think it’s possible to conceive of a new, better EA world emerging out of the SBF, and other crises, one set up well for its next stage of growth. To me, that looks like an impartial market centre &#8211; or hub &#8211; that promotes the general ideas of EA, maintains a level playing field, and keeps the community healthy. And it involves the ‘spokes’, the participants, developing and sharing their ideas for how to do the most good. What&#8217;s more, it certainly helps me, and I think it might help others, to see their involvement in effective altruism as participating in a market, rather than as an all-encompassing part of their identity.</p>
<p>I also suspect that, if EA is going to survive its many crises and retain some credibility, it needs to make some changes. The attitude I’ve observed from some leading EA is, effectively, “SBF was a bad guy, we were unlucky, things are basically fine. Let’s wait for this to blow over”. I find that disappointing. As Winston Churchill once said, &#8220;never let a good crisis go to waste&#8221;. I fear effective altruists are, collectively, letting this crisis go to waste.</p>
<p>I’ve sketched some basic ideas and I’m curious to hear what people think about them. I’ve deliberately not got into the details of what a free market for maximum altruism would look like, both because that’s not my area and because I want people to focus on the big picture. But I would welcome economists and others to launch themselves at this task in due course.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/what-is-effective-altruism-how-could-it-be-improved/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rich People’s Gain is Worth Less Than Poor People’s Pain</title>
		<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/rich-peoples-gain-is-worth-less-than-poor-peoples-pain/</link>
					<comments>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/rich-peoples-gain-is-worth-less-than-poor-peoples-pain/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:12:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/?p=15</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tomorrow (May 22), I’m keynoting Public Knowledge’s Emerging Tech conference in DC. On Tuesday (May 23), I’ll be in TORONTO for a book launch for Red Team Blues that’s part of WEPFest, a benefit for the West End Phoenix, onstage with Dave Bidini (The Rheostatics), Ron Diebert (Citizen Lab) and the whistleblower Dr Nancy Olivieri. ... <a title="Rich People’s Gain is Worth Less Than Poor People’s Pain" class="read-more" href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/rich-peoples-gain-is-worth-less-than-poor-peoples-pain/" aria-label="More on Rich People’s Gain is Worth Less Than Poor People’s Pain">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow (May 22), I’m keynoting Public Knowledge’s Emerging Tech conference in DC.</p>
<p>On Tuesday (May 23), I’ll be in TORONTO for a book launch for Red Team Blues that’s part of WEPFest, a benefit for the West End Phoenix, onstage with Dave Bidini (The Rheostatics), Ron Diebert (Citizen Lab) and the whistleblower Dr Nancy Olivieri.</p>
<p>Utilitarianism — the philosophy of making decisions to benefit the most people — sounds commonsensical. But utilitarianism is — and always has been — an attractive nuisance, one that invites its practitioners to dress up their self-serving preferences with fancy mathematics that “prove” that their wins and your losses are “rational.”</p>
<p>That’s been there ever since Jeremy Bentham’s formulation of the concept of utilitarianism, which he immediately mobilized in service to the panopticon, his cruel design for a prison where prisoners would be ever haunted by a watcher’s unseeing eye. Bentham seems to have sincerely believed that there was a utilitarian case for the panopticon, which let him declare his sadistic thought-experiment (thankfully, it was never built during Bentham’s life) to be a utility-maximizing act of monumental kindness.</p>
<p>Ever since Bentham, utilitarianism has provided cover for history’s great monsters to claim that they were only acting in service to the greater good.</p>
<p>Think of Larry Summers’ infamous 1991 memo where he, in his capacity as chief economist of the World Bank, proposed dumping toxic waste in poor countries:</p>
<p>The measurements of the costs of health impairing pollution depends on the foregone earnings from increased morbidity and mortality. From this point of view a given amount of health impairing pollution should be done in the country with the lowest cost, which will be the country with the lowest wages. I think the economic logic behind dumping a load of toxic waste in the lowest wage country is impeccable and we should face up to that.</p>
<p>Translation: people in poor countries are already sick, and will not feel the additional health burdens from toxic waste as keenly as hale, well-fed rich people will.</p>
<p>Summers later claimed that this was sarcasm, saying it was “never intended in any way as a serious policy recommendation,” and “no sane person favors dumping toxic waste near where anybody lives or thinks that places could be made better off with more toxic waste.”</p>
<p>But Summers’ signature on that memo was no aberration: under the World Bank’s tender ministrations, postcolonial nations were often required to relax their antipollution rules, and the Summers memo is best understood as “saying the quiet part aloud.”</p>
<p>Much of utilitarianism’s appeal lies in quantifying squishy, qualitative factors. It lets us create measures like the quality-adjusted life year (QALY), which is used to decide how much resources should be allocated to preserving someone’s life.</p>
<p>The underlying question the QALY seeks to clarify is an important one: do you want to (for example) undergo a year of painful, debilitating cancer treatments in order to prolong your life by slightly more than a year? Or would you rather forego the cancer treatment and instead manage your pain and have a final year of relative comfort in which to make your goodbyes and wind up your affairs?</p>
<p>For a beautiful mediation on this subject, see Atul Gawande’s brilliant book Being Mortal, or listen to the BBC Reith Lecture he gave on the subject. One thing Gawande’s book makes clear is that the “utility” of different courses of action are intensely personal, and there’s no way to assess them in a mathematical vacuum. Quantizing the qualitative elements of that decision is a lossy process, one with potentially catastrophic consequences, as anyone who’s ever grappled with a private health insurer’s decision to reject a treatment recommended by your doctor can attest.</p>
<p>Like “realism,” utilitarianism is often code for “being a selfish jerk.” Think of “longtermism,” which concerns itself with a hypothetical future containing trillions of synthetic, simulated humans living inside computers. Making each of those synthetic people very slightly happier will produce a gigantic aggregate benefit.</p>
<p>Even a very small amount of additional happiness multiplied by trillions of imaginary people adds up to more happiness than all of the people currently alive can ever experience. By that reasoning, there’s no amount of misery one could inflict on today’s living people that would outweigh even the chance of bringing a dollop of joy to those far-future sims.</p>
<p>For the selfish, utilitarianism works best when it provides a justification for making themselves better off at others’ expense. At first blush, longtermism militates for everyone to don hairshirts in support of the happiness of those trillions of future sims.</p>
<p>But longtermism is an offshoot of “effective altruism” (whose leading spokescriminal and financier was Sam Bankman-Fried), which offers an ingenious solution to this problem: earning to give.</p>
<p>“Earning to give” is the utilitarian, effective altruist notion that one should take the highest-paying job one can get, even if that job involves inflicting untold misery through pollution, inequality and exploitation — provided that you eventually give all the gains away to good causes that outweigh the harm you did while earning them.</p>
<p>And since succeeding as (say) a high-powered investment banker requires that you wear the finest clothes, drive a showy car, live in a fancy home, fly first class and eat at Michelin-starred restaurants, all of these comforts can be explained as utilitarian necessities one must endure on the path to earning enough to give away so much that you make lots of people better off.</p>
<p>This is utilitarianism as unintentional self-parody, but it’s also another example of “saying the quiet part aloud.” The greatest monsters of history —men like Andrew Carnegie, JP Rockefeller, Henry Ford and Andrew Mellon — lived lives of cruel mass-exploitation, only to rehabilitate their reputations at the ends of their lives, or posthumously, by endowing charitable foundations that do genuinely good works, while plastering those monsters’ names on every tangible expression of those works.</p>
<p>Our modern crop of monsters are pursuing the same path: from Bill Gates to Warren Buffett, monopolist wreckers devote considerable energy to making their names synonymous with charity, not the cruelty by which they won their fortunes (the Sackler opioid family tried this gambit, but failed, thanks to tireless activism from their victims and their victims’ families).</p>
<p>The Gates/Buffett pitch is just “earning-to-give” by another name: “Yes, these men destroyed countless lives to enrich themselves, but they plan to give (most of) the booty away to make other lives better, wiping away their sins.”</p>
<p>An intellectually honest utilitarian would trade place with the poorest, most abused person if it resulted in a net gain to the world’s supply of happiness. But these honest utilitarians are few and far between.</p>
<p>Here’s a daring litmus test for honest utilitarianism, courtesy of the US Office of Management and Budget (OMB), the agency charged with weighing federal programs to determine whether they represent value for money.</p>
<p>In a draft circular, the OMB proposes that these calculations should be weighted to account for the “marginal utility” to the beneficiaries of each program.</p>
<p>This may sound complex, but it’s quite straightforward. Here’s John Quiggin’s summary:</p>
<p>A project that delivers a dollar of benefits to each of a group of poor people is worth more than a project that delivers a dollar of benefits to each of a group of rich people.</p>
<p>This relies on a simple and irrefutable utilitarian observation: an additional dollar does less for someone who can afford all the necessities of life than it does to someone who has to choose between, say, buying groceries and paying the rent.</p>
<p>If you’ve got a million dollars in the bank, the additional dollar only causes the number in your bank balance to rise by one. You might experience a brief, warm glow when this happens, but that’s nothing compared to the difference that a poor person experiences if the same dollar makes the difference between eviction and homelessness, and staying put in their family home.</p>
<p>These marginal utility calculations are a well-understood, widely accepted economic fundamental, and we can use them to calculate the multipliers that the OMB could use to estimate the value of each program based on its beneficiaries.</p>
<p>Kevin Drum did just that, with an accompanying chart:</p>
<p>Kevin Drum’s chart showing “the value of a dollar at different income levels,” ranging from 15.25X for households earning $10,000 or less to 0.02x for households earning $1 million or more.<br />
Kevin Drum<br />
As Quiggin explains, this method would produce some pretty startling policy recommendations:</p>
<p>If a policy halved Elon Musk’s income, while doubling the income of a single randomly chosen US household, it would be evaluated as neutral. If the policy doubled the income of two households, it would be beneficial.</p>
<p>In a thread dissecting the circular, Noah Kaufman writes, “this isn’t just an assumption tweak. It’s an entirely different approach to cost-benefit analysis.”</p>
<p>Both Quiggin and Drum assume that this will face stiff opposition and likely fail to become policy (Drum: “the usual suspects will have something to say before long. I predict that they will be very pissed off.” Quiggin: “it is almost certain to be killed off”).</p>
<p>But as Quiggin points out, the underlying utilitarian logic is impeccable. Any self-styled utilitarian who doesn’t have a good answer for why this method shouldn’t be the default forfeits their much-vaunted claim to rationality.</p>
<p>Catch me on tour with Red Team Blues in DC, Toronto, Oxford, Hay, Manchester, Nottingham, London, and Berlin!</p>
<p>Cory Doctorow (craphound.com) is a science fiction author, activist, and blogger. He has a podcast, a newsletter, a Twitter feed, a Mastodon feed, and a Tumblr feed. He was born in Canada, became a British citizen and now lives in Burbank, California. His latest nonfiction book is Chokepoint Capitalism (with Rebecca Giblin), a book about artistic labor market and excessive buyer power. His latest novel for adults is Attack Surface. His latest short story collection is Radicalized. His latest picture book is Poesy the Monster Slayer. His latest YA novel is Pirate Cinema. His latest graphic novel is In Real Life. His forthcoming books include Red Team Blues, a noir thriller about cryptocurrency, corruption and money-laundering (Tor, 2023); and The Lost Cause, a utopian post-GND novel about truth and reconciliation with white nationalist militias (Tor, 2023).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/rich-peoples-gain-is-worth-less-than-poor-peoples-pain/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scenic Devon resort famed for its black swans is seaside gem</title>
		<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/scenic-devon-resort-famed-for-its-black-swans-is-seaside-gem/</link>
					<comments>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/scenic-devon-resort-famed-for-its-black-swans-is-seaside-gem/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:11:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/?p=12</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A picturesque seaside town in Devon is loved by local residents, as well as visitors. Dawlish is located about 13 miles from Exeter and whether people have lived there for months or years, they have nothing but praise for the area and have welcomed all of the latest additions like the new play park for ... <a title="Scenic Devon resort famed for its black swans is seaside gem" class="read-more" href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/scenic-devon-resort-famed-for-its-black-swans-is-seaside-gem/" aria-label="More on Scenic Devon resort famed for its black swans is seaside gem">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A picturesque seaside town in Devon is loved by local residents, as well as visitors. Dawlish is located about 13 miles from Exeter and whether people have lived there for months or years, they have nothing but praise for the area and have welcomed all of the latest additions like the new play park for children, and the ongoing seawall.</p>
<p>Famous for its black swans, the Dawlish water is bursting with wildlife and is a buzzing and vibrant place to visit, while also having a nice community vibe. As you walk along the riverside, or the beach, there is always someone who will say hello or simply give you a smile that can really brighten up someone&#8217;s day.</p>
<p>After visiting the quirky and quaint town, we discovered this is a brilliant place for all ages with its many attractions, from The Waterfowl to the town&#8217;s high street featuring mostly, friendly local businesses. Additionally, the new play park along the river came up in conversation often and appears to be a great new addition for families and holidaymakers.</p>
<p>One resident, who has lived in Dawlish for more than 30 years, told us how the shop owners get to know you, compared the city life where you can be a &#8220;stranger.&#8221;</p>
<p>Along the Dawlish river, we met Gillian Burgess, 54, who moved from Exeter to Dawlish, with her son aged 22, around four months ago. She told us that she would find it hard to move back to the big city after living in a small quirky town and praised it for being well looked after. Gillian was walking three dogs, who she was dog sitting, called Lulu, Rio and Daphne and also mentioned how welcomed she has felt by local business owners.</p>
<p>A &#8220;picturesque&#8221; seaside town in Devon is loved by local residents, as well as visitors<br />
A &#8220;picturesque&#8221; seaside town in Devon is loved by local residents, as well as visitors (Image: Zhara Simpson)<br />
Gillian told us: &#8220;I moved down from Exeter three to four months ago. I think the difference with Dawlish is that it&#8217;s really clean and tidy, and especially living opposite the waterway, the area, the pavements, the streets, the gardens are really well looked after. In Exeter they leave everything to grow on the sidewalks, it&#8217;s a hay fever city with pollen and bugs, but down here, it&#8217;s well looked after.</p>
<p>&#8220;We are so lucky because you have the waterway which you can walk alongside, and the beach literally two minutes away, so you have a choice. People in the area are also really friendly, having just moved in, some of the local business owners look out for you, I&#8217;ve had free chips and things like that, so there is that community feel as well.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;ve also noticed that there are a lot of people who do regular things, it&#8217;s the same faces who are going for breakfasts in the morning, there is just a nice community vibe. You notice on the bridge, there are things going on and there are events to take part in on the lawn, so there is a lovely community feel. It would be quite hard to move back to Exeter now.&#8221;</p>
<p>Gillian Burgess on her morning walk on the Dawlish Water<br />
Gillian Burgess on her morning walk on the Dawlish Water (Image: Zhara Simpson)<br />
Talking about what it&#8217;s like to walk dogs in the area, she said: &#8220;There are so many different smells, they like the beach and they&#8217;re happy. Although we don&#8217;t have a garden anymore, the waterway is our garden now so we will come out and sit in the sunshine.</p>
<p>&#8220;Dawlish has a quirky kind of charm, a really good community feel to it, very friendly and you have the beach. It gets very busy when the holiday makers are down here, you notice that and when you look out of your window, it&#8217;s like Exeter high street. I&#8217;ve experienced the Bank Holidays, but the thing is, with that, it&#8217;s still a nice vibe because people have come down to relax and enjoy. So it&#8217;s a place where you come to be happy. and even when it&#8217;s busy, there is still that nice vibe about it which is good.&#8221;</p>
<p>Mum Kate lives in Dawlish with her partner and two children who are three and nine months old. She said the town is a great place for children to grow up and expressed how her family are fortunate to live in the little town, adding that it is picturesque.</p>
<p>Kate explained: &#8220;I&#8217;ve lived in Dawlish for a couple of years now. It&#8217;s lovely, very quaint and there&#8217;s a real sense of community which is really nice and it&#8217;s a really lovely place for children to grow up.&#8221;</p>
<p>Describing Dawlish, she said: &#8220;It&#8217;s very picturesque and it has everything you need on your doorstep. It has the park, the beach, and lovely cafes. The sun generally shines quite a lot, so it is lovely here.</p>
<p>Discussing her favourite local businesses, she continued: &#8220;Le Cygne is really nice for coffee and beautiful food and Annie&#8217;s is amazing for supporting mothers and their children, and having such a welcoming space for your kids.</p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s just a really nice area, we feel very fortunate to live here. We&#8217;re happy here.&#8221;</p>
<p>Margret &#8216;Maggie&#8217; Meadows has lived in the beautiful town for 33 years, and said it has everything any resident could need, from shops to leisure. She also complimented the local community groups. She explained how nobody needs to &#8220;feel lonely&#8221; while living in Dawlish.</p>
<p>Maggie told us: &#8220;I&#8217;ve lived in Dawlish since 1990. I love it here, it does everything for me, you&#8217;ve got shops, leisure, near a hospital, doctors, a theatre, museum, everything, in a small area, and the sea of course.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/scenic-devon-resort-famed-for-its-black-swans-is-seaside-gem/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Good and Bad of Effective Altruism</title>
		<link>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/the-good-and-bad-of-effective-altruism/</link>
					<comments>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/the-good-and-bad-of-effective-altruism/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/?p=9</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Effective Altruism (EA) concerns itself with answering the question: how can we use our resources to help others the most? As Effective Altruists, we want to give in the manner that will benefit the most people by the largest amount. Typically that means investing (money, skills, influence) in areas that are under-resourced, that wouldn’t otherwise ... <a title="The Good and Bad of Effective Altruism" class="read-more" href="https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/the-good-and-bad-of-effective-altruism/" aria-label="More on The Good and Bad of Effective Altruism">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Effective Altruism (EA) concerns itself with answering the question: how can we use our resources to help others the most?</p>
<p>As Effective Altruists, we want to give in the manner that will benefit the most people by the largest amount.</p>
<p>Typically that means investing (money, skills, influence) in areas that are under-resourced, that wouldn’t otherwise receive investment and which provide a high-degree of certainty that the good will happen.</p>
<p>This approach to giving has some very strong advantages as well as several notable disadvantages:</p>
<p>Advantages</p>
<p>More good for the same investment — arguably 100x increase in altruistic ROI. We know that the best charities are hundreds of times more effective at improving lives than merely good charities; donating to these charities can hugely increase the amount of good that a donation can do.<br />
Less suffering — tackling the most problematic problems upfront will result in the least human suffering.<br />
Highlighting fact-based interventions can help to recruit rational donators who may previously have been reluctant to donate due to uncertainty of the good that their donation will do.<br />
Secondary effects such as bringing visibility to charity efficacy, thus encouraging charities to justify the efficacy of their operations (and not just their operational efficiency).<br />
Disadvantages</p>
<p>Some effective causes, that currently lack evidence may be neglected.<br />
Domestic efforts to serve those in need, may be neglected.<br />
Feedback from EA donations can be less tangible than donations to or volunteering at domestic charities, reducing the feel-good factor associated with altruism. This has the potential to reduce donations.<br />
Funding for advanced research funding for many (long-tail) diseases may decrease.<br />
Smaller charitable endeavours which key EA organisations lack the resources to assess may be neglected.<br />
Pursuing a career in a lucrative industry in order to be able to give more in the future (a tactic sometimes suggested in EA) may result in no future donations and potentially net negative if the chosen industry is a force for social harm. Dissuading people from offering their support for a given cause in favour of a more impactful one can be counterproductive, leading them to feel disillusioned about charitable giving.<br />
The disadvantages of Effective Altruism are certainly valid concerns.</p>
<p>However, as effective altruists we believe in impact. That doing the most good is what is important, even if that may not necessarily be the approach that makes us feel best.</p>
<p>For further reading on Effective Altruism try the following books:</p>
<p>Doing Good Better<br />
The Most Good you can Do<br />
The Life you can Save<br />
For a more comprehensive overview of the key criticisms of Effective Altruism see here:</p>
<p>[Criticism of effective altruism — EA Wiki](Criticism of effective altruism)<br />
Thank you for Reading <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f64f-1f3fb.png" alt="🙏🏻" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /><br />
If you enjoyed this, you might like The Deployment Age — a weekly update of tools and musings that shine some light on the emerging technologies and trends of the 2020s.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://staging.effectivealtruism.org/2023/06/03/the-good-and-bad-of-effective-altruism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
